混沌初世，一片黑暗
male narraor: In the beginning, there was darkness,
接着，发生爆炸
and then, bang,
产生了无边无际的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间、空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
有一个地方，每天都有新发现
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
但它依然极端神秘，让人饶有兴趣
the ind-blowing, the deadly secrets
它就是宇宙
of a place we call The Universe.
彗星撞击海洋导致了
Did a comet slamming into the ocean
圣经所说的大洪水？
cause the biblical flood?
海啸引发的波浪至少有50米高
- The tsunami wave itself was at least 50 meters high.
一个太空火球
narrator: Did a fiery messenger from space
逆转了基督教的命运？
reverse the fate of Christianity?
一颗时速70,000英里的流星
- Suddenly, at 70,000 miles per hour,
突如其来地撞向地球
this meteor comes crashing to Earth.
天空中的火球
narrator: Did a fireball in the sky
彻底摧毁了最早的北美居民？
wipe out the first North Americans?
太空确实是一次次地改变了历史
- Space literally has changed history time and time again.
一个独立的科研小组正在展开研究....
narrator: A maverick group of scientists is on a quest...
超巨型彗星的撞击
- Very large comet impacts
改变了人类文明的发展方向
could have changed the course of human civilization.
反主流科学的研究
narrator: A quest to defy mainstream science
证明了人类历史
and prove that human history
因为从天而降的灾难
was rocked with catastrophic moments,
而被改变
when space changed history.
=========记录片之家倾情奉献=========
========http://www.jlpzj.net========
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
《宇宙：太空改变历史》
40天40夜的滂沱大雨
40 days and 40 nights of torrential rains.
圣经的大洪水故事和吉尔伽美什史诗
The Bible's great flood and the Epic of Gilgamesh
都描述到一个广为人知的
are widespread myths that depict an event
人类遭到彻底灭绝的神话
that wiped humanity off the face of the Earth.
这只是一个神话
But was it simply a myth,
还是确有其事？
or did it really happen?
假如真是如此，科学家又如何去解释它呢？
And if so, how can science explain such a catastrophe?
没有任何理由能说明，超巨型彗星撞击
- There's no reason that very large comet impacts
在过去的15,000年间不会出现
could not have occurred during the last 15,000 years.
它应当发生过
And there could have been, even,
甚至还引发了全球性的灾难
a globally catastrophic event
改变了人类的发展进程
that could have changed the course of human civilization.
考古学家布鲁斯.马赛
narrator: Archeologist Bruce Masse
参加了由特立独行的科学家所组成的
is a member of a small group of maverick scientists
“全新世撞击工作组”
called the Holocene Impact Working Group.
“全新世”是地质术语，用于表示
It's named for the Holocene Epoch,
从10,000年前开始的地质时期
which began 10,000 years ago.
马赛的组织让天文学领域躁动不已
His group has roiled the world of astronomy
因为它宣称灾难性的撞击
by claiming that catastrophic impacts
远比人们想象的要频繁得多
have occurred much more often than supposed
并因此改变了人类的历史进程
and have actually changed the course of human history.
大洪水就是例证
Case in point: the great flood.
圣经的诺亚方舟故事
The biblical story of Noah's ark
只是全世界众多的古神话
is simply one version of an ancient story that's found in dozens of myths and legends
其中的一个版本
across the globe.
我曾经潜心去
- What I decided to do is to take a look
研究世界各地的洪水神话
at this worldwide distribution of flood myths, take a sample of those myths,
并收集了175个地方的相关传说
and the sample I selected was 175 locations from across the world.
这些洪水神话
narrator: Most of these flood myths
绝大多数惊人地相似
contain striking similarities,
都有描述到
including the common legend
洪水发生之前
that just before the flood began,
一个拖着大尾巴的天外之物
a celestial creature with impressive tails,
横过天空
raced across the sky.
他们没有科学的彗星知识
- Since they didn't have a science to understand what comets were all about,
就理所当然地去解释
they would try to come up with a natural solution.
因此，彗星有可能被当成了蛇
So therefore, a comet might be a snake.
众所周知，彗星有尾巴
narrator: Comets are known to have tails.
它带来了另外两个作用：
The visible effect of two byproducts:
尘埃反射阳光
dust reflecting sunlight
并产生电离气体
and glowing ionized gases
气体在后面咆哮着，如同喷气式飞机的凝结尾
roaring off the back like jet contrails.
有趣的是
- Interestingly enough,
你能看到所谓的“逆向彗尾”
you can actually have what's called an anti-tail,
从我们的角度看，彗尾就好象是
where, from our point of view, it looks like the tail of the comets
朝着两个完全不同的方向
are actually pointing in two totally different directions.
太阳散发的辐射
So as solar radiation streams off of our sun,
把物质从彗星里蒸发出来
it tends to make the material that's evaporating off of the comet
朝太阳方向伸展
appear to recede away from the Sun.
在地球上的某些地方会观察到
narrator: As seen from certain spots on the Earth,
尘埃尾巴有时会弯成弧形
the dust tail can sometimes curve around
因此它似乎是反向的
so that it appears to point in the opposite direction.
所以，地球上的观察者
- So observers on Earth
会见到一个物体
would see an object
它看起来好象是头戴饰物
in which it looked like there was a head with a headdress
或者是头上有角
or a horn coming out of its head.
在北美和南美的神话中
In North American mythology, South American mythology,
它是一条头上长角的蛇
it's a serpent with a horn on it's head.
在印度，它是一条头上有巨角的鱼
In Hindu, it's a fish with a giant horn on it's head.
在大多数神话中，随之而来的是
narrator: In most myths, the creature's arrival
一场几乎彻底毁灭世界的
was followed by a watery disaster
洪水灾难
that almost destroyed the world.
仔细审视这个神话
- If you look at other aspects of this mythology,
你会发现，它讲述的是黑暗、飓风级的强风
it's talking about, then, darkness, hurricane-force winds.
还有滂沱大雨
It's talking about torrential rainfall.
以及海啸
Talking about tsunamis.
现在，如果把所有信息叠加在一起...
Now, if you add all of that information together...
这就说明
These are the properties that you would get
彗星曾深度撞击海洋
from a deep water ocean impact of a comet.
如果一颗彗星曾撞击海洋
- If a comet were to strike in the open ocean,
巨大的能量会转移到
you would really get a massive amount of energy
撞击地点的海水
delivered into that part of the ocean that it hit.
巨量的水
narrator: The amount of water
会注入到大气层
injected into the atmosphere would be colossal.
在铁匠铺的锻造车间里
- We're here visiting a forge in a blacksmith shop
我们将演示
to show what would happen when a comet comes in
彗星以高速撞击海洋
at high speeds and impacts the ocean,
传递全部动能到水里的情形
delivering all that kinetic energy into the water.
锻造车间通常
narrator: A typical forge can heat carbon steel
把碳钢加热到大约华氏2,200度
to approximately 2,200 degrees Fahrenheit.
但彗星超高速袭击
But a hypervelocity comet strike
所产生的是10,000度以上的冲击温度
will produce shock temperatures well over 10,000 degrees,
比太阳表面更热
hotter than the surface of the Sun.
太空来的彗星
- A comet coming in from outer space
会携带着巨大的动能
would be carrying with it an immense amount of kinetic energy
因为它是以极端速度移动的
because it's moving at such an extreme velocity.
当它撞击海洋
When that impacts the ocean,
能量使水蒸发
that energy is capable of vaporizing
涉及面积达数百平方公里
up to hundreds of square kilometers of water,
因而大量水蒸汽进入到外层大气中
sending plumes of steam up into the outer atmosphere.
高空大气通常只有大约0.5%的水汽
- Normally, in the upper atmosphere, there's only about a half a percent of water vapor.
现在却注入了总量惊人的新水汽
So you get this injection of this large amount of new water vapor.
随着被注入大气层的巨量的水倾泻下来
narrator: As the massive infusion of water into the atmosphere rains down,
地球就会下起长达数周或数月的
a global deluge could drown the Earth
全球性暴雨
for weeks or months.
布鲁斯.马赛认为
Bruce Masse believed he had found
自己发现了世界大洪水的可能原因...
a possible source of the worldwide flood myth...
超级彗星的侵袭
A massive comet strike.
但他缺少物理证据
But he lacked the physical evidence.
哥伦比亚大学地质学家达拉丝.艾博特
Columbia University geologist Dallas Abbott
调查着可能的宇宙弹坑
investigates potential cosmic craters.
布鲁斯.马赛收集了
- Bruce Masse had compiled
一套口述资料
a set of oral histories of catastrophic events
听起来象是宇宙撞击引发的灾难
that sounded like they were some sort of cosmic impact,
而且他发现它们的中心
and he found that the center of them
在印度洋
was around the Indian Ocean.
通过实际探测水深
narrator: Using bathymetry readings,
以及用卫星对洋底深度的变化进行测量
or satellite measurements of depth variations in the ocean floor,
艾博特精确定位了可能的撞击区域
Abbott was able to pinpoint a potential impact zone.
她把它命名为“伯克尔弹坑”
She named it Burkle crater,
以此向同校的一位同事致敬
in honor of a colleague at Columbia University.
巨大的伯克尔弹坑
Burkle is a massive depression
位于离马达加斯加海岸
located nearly 1,000 miles
大约1,000英里的地方
off the coast of Madagascar...
它的直径约为18英里
About 18 miles in diameter,
深约13,000英尺
Burkle Crater lies at a depth of approximately 13,000 feet,
难于开展大规模的研究，而且费用会很昂贵
making an extensive study difficult and expensive.
这样巨大的弹坑
But a crater this big
必然会产生超级彗星撞击的另一个影响
would produce another logical fingerprint of a massive comet impact:
超级海啸
a mega-tsunami.
彗星撞击海洋比撞击结实的地面
- A comet hitting the ocean would actually be more damaging
所产生的危害更大
than a comet hitting solid ground.
因为它会掀起排山倒海的海啸
And that's because it would send up a gigantic tsunami
猛烈撞击海岸周围的一切
that would slam into the coast all around it.
当超级海啸攻击海岸线
narrator: When massive tsunamis strike shorelines,
其迹象会保留数个世纪
the evidence can persist for centuries.
艾博特把注意力转移到马达加斯加的海岸线上
Abbott turned her attention to the shoreline of Madagascar.
在那段时间，我在马达加斯加一无所获
- At the time, I couldn't get data on Madagascar.
但随着谷歌地球的面世
But the minute Google Earth came out,
我立即前往马达加斯加考察
I went and I looked at Madagascar.
那里的海啸印记相当明显
And the tsunami deposits there were phenomenal.
我很直接地发现了
I immediately found these huge chevrons,
这些或许是世上最大的波浪印记
which I think are probably the biggest chevrons on the planet.
波浪印记是对称的沙丘
narrator: Chevrons are symmetrical sand dunes
分布在世界各地的海岸线上
found along coastlines around the world.
有人认为它们是在巨大的波浪
Some believe they form when massive waves
猛烈撞击海岸，然后退去时形成的
slam into the coast and then recede.
其独特的V字形
Their distinctive V shape
指明了波浪的方向
may even serve as a directional marker.
后向角是一个V字
- The back azimuth is a V.
这里是内陆，V字指向内陆
So this is inland. V points inland.
V字的后向角
The back azimuth of the V,
告诉你原因在哪里
that tells you where the source is.
艾博特声称原因就是
narrator: Abbott claims that source is Burkle crater,
离海岸数百英里的伯克尔弹坑
located hundreds of miles offshore.
但其它人质疑
But others doubt that tsunamis
海啸与波浪印记的关系
have anything to do with chevron formation.
许多地质学家
- The geologists that actually go to the sites
前来实地调查，仔细地考察
and do fieldwork and have looked at these,
他们认为这些与海啸无关
they don't associate those with tsunami.
只是与扬尘有关
They associate those with windblown dust.
因此我怀疑这些
And so I'm skeptical that these things
与海啸的波浪是否有关联
have anything to do with tsunami waves.
但当达拉丝.艾博特来到马达加斯加
narrator: But when Dallas Abbott traveled to Madagascar,
她在沙丘内找到了惊人的证据
she found surprising evidence trapped inside the dunes.
我们发现海啸沉淀超过200米高
- We found tsunami deposits over 200 meters high.
在这个大土坡的顶上
And when we got to the top of this big hill,
我们在沉积物中发现海产品的化石
we found marine fossils in the sediment.
在所有我们寻找过的地方
And we found it in all of the locations
都能发现它
where we looked.
飓风只能带来
Hurricanes bring in marine microfossils.
在水面生活的
But they only bring the kind
海产品的微化石
that live in the top of the water column,
但在海底生活的
whereas the kind of marine microfossils
海产品的微化石
that live on the ocean bottom,
不会因飓风之类的原因而移动
they don't get transported by things like hurricanes.
马达加斯加的化石
Well, the Madagascar fossils are dominated
由海底的海产品所形成
by the ones that live on the bottom.
因此，它们毫无疑问地不是风刮来的
And so they absolutely can't be just windblown fossils.
对全新世小组的成员来说
narrator: For members of the Holocene group,
波浪印记和微化石
the chevrons and the microfossil evidence
就是确凿的证据
are the smoking gun.
把它们与世界各地的
When connected to the flood myths
大洪水古神话联系起来
of ancient societies around the world,
呈现出来的是一幅扣人心弦的景象
they help paint a compelling picture.
“洪水-彗星”假说
But the flood-comet hypothesis
与许多天文学家固有的信念相抵触
contradicts the firm beliefs of many astronomers.
宇宙撞击天文学家们，比如马克・博斯劳
Cosmic impact astronomers like Mark Boslough
就认为灾难性的撞击
believe that catastrophic impacts
在过去的15,000年间
during the last 15,000 years
根本没有发生过
simply never happened.
声称在全新世期间，在人类历史上，
- Anybody who would claim that there have been
发生过大规模破坏环境的撞击
environmentally damaging impacts during the Holocene,
的那些人有强烈的责任
during the era of humans,
来进行举证
has a very high burden of proof
因为这样的事情
because the probability that such a thing
哪怕只发生一次，可能性也很小
even once would have happened is very small.
我的回答是，特别的主张
- The response has been that extraordinary claims
需要有特别的证据
require extraordinary evidence,
没有人会相信那是一个撞击坑
because nobody believes that an impact crater is confirmed
除非你在那里
until you actually go to the crater
能找到撞击熔体的样本
and you've got samples of the impact melt body.
我们现在还没有
We still, at the moment,
获得证明伯克尔弹坑的证据
don't have the evidence to prove Burkle Crater.
与此同时
narrator: In the meantime,
全新世撞击工作组认为
the Holocene Impact Working Group
它已经找到了年代更近的证据
believes it has found evidence of a far more recent impact.
这个证据
The evidence, they say,
就埋在格陵兰岛的雪层下
lies buried in the ice sheets of Greenland.
这个证据表明，是一颗彗星
And, they say it points to a comet
把欧洲推进了野蛮黑暗的
that helped push Europe into the barbarism
中世纪
of the Dark Ages.
=========翻译/时间轴:annwayili=========
（如有不当，请多包涵，不吝指导！谢谢！）
在改变地球历史的
In the search for extraterrestrial impacts
外星撞击的探索上
that have changed history,
雄辩代替不了事实
certain facts are not in dispute.
在公元535年的某个时候
Sometime in the year 535 A.D.,
某些物体有如灰色的面纱
something descended like a gray veil
笼罩着整个地球
over planet Earth.
它让地球进入了近2,000年以来
It created the most severe cooling period
最寒冷的时期
of the last 2,000 years
使人类陷入了前所未有的危机
and plunged humanity into an unprecedented crisis.
在那期间
- During that time period,
非常非常多的灰
a very, very large quantity of ash
严严实实地掩盖着地球
completely enshrouds the Earth.
它阻止了阳光的照射
It cuts sunlight off from crops
that are growing on the ground.
耕地里的庄稼纷纷死去
It kills off crops that are under cultivation.
它导致了饥荒
It leads to famine because it interrupts
当时人类社会的粮食生产
the ability to produce food for the civilizations
无法得到保障
that were present on the planet at the time.
据历史记载，那是在公元536年初
- We know from historical data that starting early in 536 A.D.,
太阳变得非常昏暗
the Sun became very dim.
在美索不达米亚，太阳持续18个月昏暗
And in Mesopotamia, the sun was dim for 18 months.
在那个时期里
And they said that during that time period,
太阳每天只出现4个小时
the Sun came out for about four hours a day.
没有太阳的岁月，它的烙印
narrator: The signature of this year without the Sun
在今天还可以看到
remains to the present day.
爱尔兰和加利福尼亚的树木年轮
Tree ring data from Ireland and California
清楚地显示着那段全球严寒时期的影响
shows the unmistakable signs of dramatic global cooling.
树木年轮清楚表明
- The tree ring evidence clearly illustrates
在六世纪有一段时期
that there was a period in the sixth century
原本营养可让树木强壮
where nutrients that make a tree robust,
茁壮成长
that make it grow quickly,
但此时却逐渐变少到非常低的水平
those nutrients dwindled down to a very, very low level.
因此树轮极其紧密地靠在一起
And so the tree rings are extremely close together.
公认的理论
narrator: The accepted theory
把原因归咎于一次巨大的火山爆发
blames a massive volcanic eruption
引发全球性的烟灰云
and a global ash cloud.
但撞击研究者达拉丝.艾博特
But impact researcher Dallas Abbott
基于波浪印记
has proposed another culprit,
V形沙丘
beginning with evidence based on chevrons,
这些超级海啸的证据
the V-shaped sand dunes
指出凶手另有其人
that some believe are evidence for a mega-tsunami.
有一组波浪印记
One set of chevrons
位于澳大利亚的卡奔塔利亚湾
is located in Australia's Gulf of Carpentaria.
我查看了
- I looked in satellite altimetry
该处的卫星图
for something in that part of the gulf,
上面的波浪印记指向一个很小的区域
because the chevrons were pointing to a very, very small area.
我立即发现海底的这两个圆坑
And immediately, I found these two round holes in the bottom of the gulf.
经过测量
narrator: The craters measured
弹坑的直径分别为7英里和11英里
7 and 11 miles in diameter, respectively.
对沉积物的详细研究表明
A detailed study of sediments
其与外星侵袭有关
pointed to an extraterrestrial invader.
这一个深海矿样
- This is a deep sea core sample,
与卡奔塔利亚湾的相同
like the ones we studied in the Gulf of Carpentaria.
在我们筛选卡奔塔利亚湾的样品时
And when we sieved the Gulf of Carpentaria samples,
我们发现少量的岩石
we found little bits of rock,
少量的玻璃
we found little bits of glass,
以及一些惊人的矿物
and we also found some shock minerals.
并伴有许多的撞击迹象
And together, these are indications of an impact.
它们说明了事件大约发生在1,500年前
And they suggested the event was about 1,500 years ago.
所以我认为事件是在公元536年发生
And I knew about this climate event in 536 A.D.
我心想，“如果从冰芯里”
And I thought, "Well, it would be really nice
“能找到一些东西，那就太好了”
to look at an ice core to see if we can see something."
冰芯是冷藏地球气候数据的“档案柜”
narrator: An ice core is planet Earth's frozen filing cabinet of climate data,
蕴藏着数世纪的空气微粒和藻类
trapping centuries' worth of airborne particles and algae.
在远离卡奔塔利亚湾的
- We found samples from Greenland,
格陵兰岛上
which is about as far away as you can get on the planet
我们收集了许多样本
from that site in the Gulf of Carpentaria.
冰芯提供了惊人的证据
narrator: The ice cores yielded startling evidence,
包括和卡奔塔利亚湾一模一样的
including magnetized melted rock called spherules
磁性熔岩球体
that matched those retrieved in the Gulf of Carpentaria,
两种在高能撞击中形成的玻璃
two types of glass that appear to have formed in a high-energy impact,
以及一种不应该出现的
and a misplaced diatom,
只存于热带地区的硅藻海微化石
a marine microfossil that exists only in the tropics.
生长在热带到亚热带的硅藻
- So why should you be getting diatoms
为什么在格陵兰岛
that originated in the tropics to subtropics
各处都能发现？
all the way to Greenland?
没有人能够给出
Nobody has ever found diatoms in Greenland
个中原因
that came from the tropics to subtropics.
这些显微镜下的证据
narrator: The microscopic evidence
指向了外星的撞击
pointed to a celestial impact.
情况就是，一场大爆炸
- What happens is, you get a huge explosion,
把这些物质被抛进大气
and then this material goes up into the air
飘到数百甚至数千公里之外
and travels for hundreds or even thousands of kilometers.
最后沉降下来
And then it's- you know, settles out.
对宇宙撞击来说
narrator: For a cosmic impactor
要产生相似于公元535年的
to create a global atmospheric effect
那一次全球性大气影响
like the one suspected in 535 A.D.,
撞击物必须有足够的质量和速度
it must have enough mass and velocity
才能产生巨大的爆炸
to create an epic explosion.
高速和低速撞击，它们的区别在于
- The difference between a high-velocity and a low-velocity impact
低速撞击不产生爆炸
is, a low velocity impact does not create an explosion.
它会产生一个弹坑
It can make a crater,
但不是爆裂弹坑
but it's not an explosion crater.
我们现在要模拟
What we're doing here is setting up
超高速撞击
to do a simulation of a hypervelocity impact
形成弹坑的情形
in the formation of a crater.
我们用硝酸铵混合燃油
And we're using ammonium nitrate mixed with fuel oil,
当点燃它时
so when we set it off,
它会爆炸并产生一个大坑
it's gonna explode and make a huge crater.
巨大的爆炸使得大量碎屑纷纷扬扬地
It's a massive explosion that creates a big plume of debris
散落到了周围几英里的地方
that gets scattered for many, many miles around.
如果这是最极端的撞击，将是全球性的事件
And for the biggest impacts, it's a global phenomenon.
假如这个弹坑是撞击形成的
If this crater had been actually formed by an impact,
它会是爆裂性的弹坑
it would be an explosion crater,
因为来自天空的物体
because the object coming from the sky
速度极快，动能极高
is going so fast with so much kinetic energy
它会穿入地表
that it penetrates below the surface
然后变热、汽化和爆炸
and heats up, vaporizes, and explodes.
发生在澳大利亚浅水区的高速撞击
narrator: A high-velocity strike in the shallow waters off Australia
其爆炸威力之大
could have produced an explosion
足以将沉淀物和微粒
large enough to launch sediments and particulates
抛入大气层
high into the atmosphere.
抛起的高度非常高
- You can imagine that that'll get kicked up really high
大量的颗粒物质上升到了
and that you'll have a lot of particulate matter
高层大气里
up in the high atmosphere,
可谓是遮天蔽日
where it can block out a lot of the sun.
公元535年的惨剧
narrator: The disastrous events of 535 A.D.
看起来象是撞击惹的祸
seem to fit the signature of an impact
造成太阳昏暗
followed by a dimming of the sun.
但在论证
But finding the proof
一切皆因宇宙撞击而起
that it all started with a cosmic impact
这一观点的时候
is more difficult,
有一个问题成了主要的拦路虎
especially when one glaring question remains.
巨大的太空岩石
What massive space rock
能产生并排在一起的
could produce two craters
两个弹坑吗？
side by side?
他们被主流的天文学术界视为另类分子
They are considered heretics in the mainstream world of astronomy.
但全新世撞击工作组的科学家们
But the scientists belonging to the Holocene Impact Working Group
仍在不屈不挠地
are determined to prove
去证明太空改变过人类历史
that space has changed human history.
公元535年也许会发生这样的事件
One such event may have happened in the year 535 A.D.,
太阳骤然昏暗
when a sudden darkening of the sun
庄稼失收
caused crops to fail,
全球陷入饥荒
leading to worldwide famine.
树轮数据证明了惨剧曾经上演
Scientific tree ring data proves the catastrophe happened.
但科学家尚未找出幕后黑手
But science has yet to determine what actually caused it.
在2008年，宇宙撞击研究者达拉丝.艾博特
In 2008, cosmic impact researcher Dallas Abbott
发现了澳大利亚卡奔塔利亚湾的
discovered what appeared to be two huge craters
两个巨大弹坑
in Australia 's Gulf of Carpentaria.
她认为这是彗星造成的
She believes they were put there by a comet.
主流观点认为撞击非常罕见
- Well, the mainstream idea is that impacts are very rare
而且大多数的撞击是小行星引发的
and that most of the impacts that happen are asteroidal.
但我们收集的资料认为
But the data that we're finding suggest
这是彗星撞击
that the impactors that hit were cometary
不是行星撞击
rather than asteroids.
由岩石、气体、尘埃和冰构成的彗星
narrator: Composed of rock, gases, dust, and ice,
在突然遭遇到
comets are known to break apart
地球这样的大物体时
when they encounter the gravitational pull
会由于万有引力而支离破碎
of large objects like planets.
1992年7月，哈勃太空望远镜
In July of 1992, the Hubble Space Telescope
刚好拍摄到这样的情形
recorded exactly this scenario.
苏梅克-列维九号彗星经过木星的时候
As comet Shoemaker-Levy 9 hurtled past Jupiter,
木星强大的万有引力
the planet's immense gravitational pull
把彗星撕碎
tore the comet apart.
苏梅克-列维九号彗星
- Comet Shoemaker-Levy 9
破裂成好几块
broke up into several dozen fragments,
其爆炸威力相当于
the most massive of which created an explosion
6百万兆吨TNT炸药
equivalent to 6 million megatons of TNT.
而现在地球上威力最大的
Now, the biggest bomb ever made on Earth
苏联“沙皇”核弹
is the Tsar Bomba by the Soviet Union,
其当量才50兆吨
which was 50 megatons.
苏梅克-列维九号的撞击
A single impact from Shoemaker-Levy 9
威力比“沙皇”大100,000多倍
was 100,000 times more powerful.
一颗苏梅克-列维九号这样的彗星
narrator: Could a Shoemaker-Levy 9 type breakup
能在卡奔塔利亚湾产生孪生的弹坑吗？
have created the dual craters in the gulf of Carpentaria?
=========记录片之家倾情奉献=========
========http://www.jlpzj.net========
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
彗的双重撞击似有其事
The hypothesized dual impacts appear to fit the comet profile.
但主流的科学家不认可
But it's not a fit with mainstream science.
彗星撞击相当罕见
- A comet impact itself is very rare-
每100万年到10亿年才发生一次
once every 100 million to billion years.
彗星群更为罕见，甚至可以说
A comet cluster would be much more rare, even, than that,
罕见得你不能期望
so rare that you wouldn't expect it to happen
在地球上会发生
on the age of the Earth.
在卡奔塔利亚湾
narrator: The search for positive verification
是否发生撞击的问题上
of an impact in the Gulf of Carpentaria
科学家一直争论不休
continues to generate scientific controversy.
但在撞击假说里，最具争议的问题却是
But no impact hypothesis is more controversial
到底是什么让著名的北美洲文明
than the question of what wiped a famed North American culture
从地球上彻底消失
from the pages of history.
在欧洲殖民者据为已有的1000年前
Millennia before European colonists claimed it as their own,
已经有移民居住在北美洲的克洛维斯
another group of immigrants dominated North America-
直到某些人或某些事情
that is, until someone or something
让他们永远消失
wiped out the Clovis people.
克洛维斯人是居住在北美洲的
- Clovis were an ancient Paleo-Indian people
史前古印第安人
that lived in North America.
有人认为他们是第一批北美洲居民
Some people believe that they were the first people to live in North America
他们越过白令陆桥而来
and that they came across the Bering Land Bridge
从美洲北部向南扩散
and radiated down into the Americas from the north, moving south.
考古文物
narrator: Archaeological evidence,
其中包括他们著名的矛
including their famed spear points,
揭示出克洛维斯人在上个大冰河时期的兴盛
reveals the Clovis people thrived during the last great ice age
他们能够捕猎大型动物
by hunting the megafauna,
包括猛玛象和乳齿象
including huge mammoths and mastodons.
在某一刻，美洲的大型动物种群
There was a moment where the population of the megafauna
突然变化
in the Americas changed.
大型动物忽然间灭绝了
The megafauna suddenly began to disappear.
与此同时
And as they went down,
克洛维斯人也消失了
they brought the Clovis down with them.
大约13,000年前
- Approximately 13,000 years ago,
发生了一些事情
something happened.
这些事情改变了环境
Something changed the environment.
而且改变得很迅速，也很彻底
It changed it rapidly and profoundly.
整个地球
And all of a sudden,
突然间进入了小冰河时期
the planet was thrown back into a little ice age.
此次气候变化，被称为“新仙女木事件”
A climatic event we call the Younger Dryas.
在冰川消融和气温回升
narrator: After many thousands of years
持续数千年之后
of retreating glaciers and warming temperatures,
新仙女木期逆转了变暖的趋势
the Younger Dryas period reversed the warming trend
对人类和动物造成了极大的伤害
and wreaked havoc on man and beast.
科学家们激烈争论
But scientists argue fiercely
这次180度大转弯的个中原因
over the reasons for this climactic U-turn,
争论得特别激烈的是
especially one hypothesis
把责任全部归咎于外太空的假说
that places the blame squarely on outer space.
克洛维斯猎人
- The Clovis hunters
已经适应了新的居住环境
were having to adapt to new conditions.
彗星在劳伦泰冰原上空爆炸
And one of those changes could have been a comet impact
改变了他们的命运
over the Laurentide ice sheet.
“克洛维斯-彗星”假说
narrator: The Clovis comet
可能是全新世撞击工作组
is perhaps the most controversial impact hypothesis
最具争议的假说
championed by the Holocene Impact Working Group.
它声称彗星侵袭
It claims that a comet strike
北美洲冰原
into the North American ice sheet
使得巨量的内陆湖水涌入海洋
allowed large freshwater lakes to drain into the ocean,
使洋流变更
altering the ocean currents
并引发了寒冷的新仙女木期
and triggering the Younger Dryas cooling period.
肯.坦可斯里
Ken Tankersley,
是辛辛那提大学的人类学家
a University of Cincinnati anthropologist,
曾在俄亥俄州西北部发现了
uncovered cosmic impact evidence in Sheriden Cave
谢里登洞穴
in northwest Ohio.
我们在这里发现了被称为黑团的层
- The layer which we found here is known as the black mat.
该层含有丰富的碳
It's a very carbon-rich layer,
那是剧烈燃烧形成的产物
which, in this case, is the result of intense burning.
它是由木炭和大约70种灰烬
It's composed of wood charcoal and the burned remains
所组成的
of approximately 70 species.
需要熊熊的大火、剧烈的燃烧
It takes an intense fire, an intense burning,
甚至爆炸
almost an explosion, if you will,
才能得到这种类型的碳
to produce this type of carbon event.
在该层中，还包含有流星碎片
narrator: The layer also contained meteor fragments.
对超级彗星撞击来说
But more importantly,
这似乎是不容质疑的有力证据
seemingly indisputable evidence for a larger cosmic impact.
我们在其中找到了冲击钻石
- We have what's called impact diamonds.
冲击钻石，也叫坠落钻石
Impact diamonds, or shatter diamonds,
是某种爆炸
occur when some type of explosion
或者是突然的迅猛撞击
or sudden impact occurs with your surface,
压缩碳物质而产生的
compressing carbon material to create these impact diamonds.
因为尺寸微小
narrator: Also called nanodiamonds
它们还被称为纳米钻石
because of their miniscule size,
是公认的宇宙撞击的强力证据
they are recognized as powerful evidence for cosmic impact.
但它们的发现引起了众多的疑问
But their discovery raises many more questions.
在北美洲发现的
- The supposed presence of nanodiamonds
纳米钻石并不是新仙女木撞击的
in certain locations of North America isn't compelling evidence
能令人信服的证据
for the Younger Dryas impact hypothesis,
因为在许多时候，确认不了这些就是
because in some cases, it's not even clear
真正的纳米钻石
that those are genuine nanodiamonds.
它们可能是仿似纳米钻石的
They may be graphite or graphene compounds
石墨或石墨烯复合物
that kind of masquerade as nanodiamonds.
“克洛维斯-彗星”的主张
narrator: The proposed Clovis comet
还似乎漏了一个物理上的大证据：
also appears to be missing one physically huge piece of evidence:
撞击弹坑
an impact crater.
迄今为止，还没有能说明问题的弹坑被发现
To date, no telltale crater has been found.
但太空岩石在撞击地球时
But space rocks don't have to impact the Earth
不一定会引发大灾难
to ignite a catastrophe.
因为这几乎无异于触发了
We know because one very nearly touched off
一场核战争
a thermonuclear war.
纵然遭到普遍的怀疑
In the face of widespread skepticism,
撞击研究小组还是坚信
a small group　of impact researchers claim
最近的宇宙大灾难
that very recent cosmic catastrophes
改变了人类历史
have changed human history.
在13,000年前的北美洲
13,000 years ago in North America,
某些事情突然把克洛维斯文化
something suddenly sent the Clovis culture
置于万劫不复的境地
into a tailspin.
一些科学家相信彗星是罪魁祸首
Some scientists believe that a comet was to blame.
但迄今为止，没有相应的撞击坑能得到确认
But to date, no impact crater has been identified.
事实上，相当多的天外之物永远到达不了地球
But some cosmic projectiles never reach the Earth.
因为它们会在堕落的过程中
Yet they can still rain down destruction
发生空中爆炸而灰飞烟灭
in the form of an air burst.
空中爆炸是流星和彗星
An air burst is when a meteoroid or a comet
在抵达地球之前
explodes in the atmosphere
在大气层中爆炸的现象
before reaching the Earth's surface.
所以不会产生弹坑
So it doesn't produce a visible crater.
1908年的通古斯事件
A truly excellent example of what is thought to have been an air burst
就是空中爆炸的经典例子
is the Tunguska event over Siberia in 1908.
它把2,000平方公里的森林夷为平地
It leveled 2,000 square kilometers of forest.
但是没有撞击坑
But there's no impact crater.
当彗星或小行星撞击地球的大气层
- When a comet or an asteroid hits the Earth's atmosphere,
就会产生一种很近似于船浪的冲击波
it actually creates a wave very much like the wave in front of a boat.
它使空气震荡
And that shockwave, the shocked air,
产生超高的温度并扩散
gets to super-high temperatures, and it radiates.
空气散发出光和红外辐射
It radiates light and infrared radiation.
然后加热彗星或者行星
And then that heats up the comet or asteroid
使之汽化
and causes it to vaporize.
即使是小如通古斯事件中的流星
narrator: Even a smaller Tunguska-sized meteor,
其直径只有大约200英尺或更大一点
around 200 or more feet in diameter,
但它空中爆炸的威力
can produce an air burst with 1,000 times more energy
比投在广岛的原子弹还大1,000倍
than the atomic bomb dropped on Hiroshima.
在通古斯撞击的13,000年前
Some 13,000 years before the Tunguska impact,
克洛维斯的彗星
the Clovis comet
是会产生类似的空中爆炸
could have delivered a similar air burst.
但漫长的岁月
But the North American landscape
会把北美大地上的所有痕迹全部抹掉
would have long ago swallowed all traces.
无论那是彗星撞击地面
Whether it was a ground-impacting comet,
空中爆炸
an air burst,
或者都不是
or neither one,
该气候事件
this climatic event
以及它对克洛维斯文化的影响
and its effect on the Clovis culture
给后人留下了一个热议的话题
remain a hotly debated topic.
但解开这个谜团非常重要
But solving the mystery is crucial,
因为在今天也会几乎没有预警地
since the same thing could happen today
发生同样的事
with little warning.
现在，假设象通古斯事件一样
- Now, an impact like the Tunguska event,
在当今纽约的上空
a 10-megaton air burst,
10兆吨当量的空中爆炸
say at 5,000 meters over New York City,
在5,000米处的地方发生
if that were to happen today,
就会导致将近2百万人死亡
would lead to the deaths of almost 2 million people,
另外有数百万人受伤
another several million people injured,
经济损失将高达数万亿元
and a couple of trillion dollars of damage.
所以，即使是小型的空中爆炸
So even air bursts, small events,
也极具毁灭性
are something that are very destructive.
在2002年爆炸的一颗小流星
narrator: In fact, they are so potentially destructive
就充分说明了它们潜在的毁灭性
that when a very small meteor exploded in 2002,
它会引发一场核战争
it could have sparked a thermonuclear war.
在2002年6月，发生了
- In June of 2002,
一个可能会严重改变地球历史的事件
an event occurred that could have changed history on Earth in a major way.
一个相当小的流星体
A rather small meteoroid,
直径可能只有数米
maybe a couple of meters in diameter
撞进地球大气层
smashed into Earth's atmosphere,
在那里发生空中爆炸
creating an air burst, an explosion up there.
在地中海东部上空的
- And this was an enormous explosion
这一次猛烈爆炸被卫星观察到了
over the Eastern Mediterranean, and it was observed by satellite.
从上空观测到这一现象
This was unusual to be over,
相当罕见
you know, a relatively populated area.
空中爆炸发生时
narrator: At the time of the air burst,
巴基斯坦和印度，这两个核武国家
Pakistan and India, two nuclear-armed countries,
正因有争议的克什米尔地区
were embroiled in a hostile military standoff
发生军事纠纷
over the disputed Kashmir region.
两国的核战争处于一触即发的状态
The world held its breath as the two nuclear powers
让整个世界为之担心
teetered on the hair-trigger brink of war.
发生在巴印两国上空的
- So had this impact occurred just a few hours earlier,
这次撞击
it was at about the right latitude
好在早了几个小时
to have been over Pakistan or India.
它会误导两者之中的一个
This could have been mistakenby either country
以为受到对方的攻击
as a launch against them.
然后他们可能会按下核按钮
And they then might have pushed the nuclear button,
导致全面的战争
launching an all-out war.
撞击会导致误会
A mistake, basically, caused by an impact.
在地中海东部事件中
narrator: Now known as the East Mediterranean Event,
科学界确信这次爆炸说明了
the blast convinced the scientific community
在核大战剑拔弩张的时候
that predicting cosmic intruders is critical
天外来客可能会挑起事端
when nuclear armageddon is at stake.
大多数撞击地球大气层的物体
- The vast majority of objects that hit
会突如其来
the Earth's atmosphere are unexpected.
大的小行星
The big asteroids,
能够引起全球灾难的
the ones that could create a global catastrophe,
我们已经差不多全都发现了
we've discovered almost all of those.
加以编号并跟踪
They're catalogued. They're tracked.
因此，我们不必担心
And so, we don't expect one of those
其中的哪一个会毫无征兆地
to come out from nowhere and hit the Earth
袭击地球
because we can see them.
但小的会让我们防不胜防
It's the small ones that can catch us by surprise.
如果其中一颗太空巨石
narrator: But how much notice can we expect
向着地球奔来
if one of these massive space rocks
能得到多大的关注呢？
moves onto a collision course with the Earth?
这是内布拉斯加州林肯的玛丽.H
That's the question that Mary H. from Lincoln, Nebraska, wanted
想知道的问题
to ask The Universe.
玛丽，这问题很有意思
- Mary, that's an interesting question.
对将要到达的彗星和小行星
We'd like to know about incoming comets and asteroids
我们要尽早知道，设法让它们转向
as far in advance as possible in order to deflect them.
目前，小行星可能会在
Now, asteroids might be found
撞击地球前的几十或几百年被发现
tens or even hundreds of years before they hit earth,
能有时间让我们从容布置
allowing plenty of time to do something about them.
彗星的到来却没有什么预兆
Comets might come in with very little warning,
我们至多有数月或一两年的时间
only a few months or a year or two at best.
我们可能来不及让它们转向
We might not be able to deflect them.
毫无疑问
narrator: There is no dispute
彗星和其它宇宙来客
that comets and other cosmic projectiles
有可能会导致灾难
have the potential to cause catastrophes.
但在现代天文学开始揭开它们的神秘之前
But before modern astronomy began to demystify them,
单从彗星或陨星来看
the mere sighting of a comet or meteorite
它们是有可能改变过人类历史的
had the potential to change human history.
公元312年
The year is 312 A.D.
辉煌的罗马帝国正处在痛苦的内战中
The mighty Roman empire is embroiled in a bitter civil war.
在战场上，康斯坦丁皇帝
Marching into battle, the emperor Constantine
将与对手马克森提的军队相遇
is about to meet the armies of his archrival, Maxentius.
帝国的政治命运此时危如累卵
The political fate of the empire is at stake.
康斯坦丁是赫赫有名的罗马皇帝
- Constantine was a Roman emperor famous for a number of things,
并不想去皈依基督教
not the least of which is his conversion to Christianity.
但他在第四世纪
Constantine's adoption of the Christian religion
对基督教实施的怀柔政策
in the fourth century is instrumental
让他的声望骤增
in the sudden popularity and the spread of that religion
也让罗马帝国忽然间转变成基督教国家
by suddenly converting the Roman empire to a Christian empire.
许多人认为康斯坦丁的重大转变
narrator: Many believe Constantine's fateful conversion
发生在他看见血十字横过太阳的时候
occurs when he sees a fiery cross above the Sun.
他认为这是基督教上帝的神迹
Interpreting this as a sign from the Christian god,
于是命令军队在盔甲上画上十字
he commands his troops to paint crosses on their shields.
康斯坦丁的军队获得了胜利
Constantine's troops emerge victorious.
不久之后，他颁布《米兰敕令》
Soon after, the emperor signs the Edict of Milan,
为基督教永远摆脱异教的形象，奠定了坚实基础
setting the stage for the ultimate triumph of Christianity over paganism.
但有些人认为康斯坦丁的所见
But some believe Constantine's vision
可以从天文学上去解释
has an astronomical explanation.
现在看来，他所见到的景象
- It's believed now that what he personally observed
其实就是流星侵袭地球
was a meteoric impact against the Earth.
他在大白天突然看到有一颗流星
That he's looking skyward in broad daylight,
正以70,000英里的时速侵袭地球
and suddenly at 70,000 miles per hour, this meteor comes crashing to Earth.
他幻想着
His vision in seeing that is-
这是神灵的兆示
he interprets it as being a divine signal.
有一个强有力的证据
narrator: There is one powerful clue
能够帮助确认这次的宇宙事件：
that could help validate this cosmic event:
弹坑
a crater.
一个地质小组在意大利中部山区
And a team of geologists may have found it
发现了它
in the hills of central Italy.
宇宙撞击
Have cosmic impacts
曾经扭转了人类历史的发展方向吗？
altered the course of human history?
这个问题在全球的天文学界，甚至是宗教界里
It's a question that provokes the world of astronomy
掀起了轩然大波
and even the world of religion.
公元312年
In the year 312 A.D.,
康斯坦丁的命运
the fate of Christianity
也许曾被宇宙事件所左右
may have been decided by cosmic intervention.
在决战前夕
Just before a decisive battle,
罗马皇帝康斯坦丁亲眼目睹了一次奇观
the Roman emperor Constantine experiences a vision.
他思索着天空里的事情
- He remembers seeing something in the sky,
并把它解释为神灵给予的兆示
and he interprets this as being a sign from god,
基督教上帝给予的兆示
a sign from the one true Christian god.
这次有重大意义的景象
narrator: Some believe this fateful vision
有人认为是
was a fiery meteor
一颗冲向地球的火球般的流星
on a collision course with the Earth.
你的所见，取决于你离得有多远
- What you would see, of course, would depend on how far away you are.
你会看到一颗非常明亮的流星
You would see an extremely bright meteor
在白天的天空中划过
coming through the sky, and you'd see it even in the daytime.
炫目的它可能和太阳一样明亮
It would be blinding, perhaps as bright as the Sun.
然后它会撞击地面，而你会看到一次大爆炸
And then it would hit the ground, and you would see a big explosion.
按照一个瑞典地质小组的说法
narrator: According to a Swedish geology team,
康斯坦丁见到流星很可能真有其事
Constantine's meteor might very well be real.
有一个弹坑作为证明
And there's a crater to prove it.
在1999年，该小组在意大利中部的高原地区
In 1999, the team discovered a mysterious body of water
发现了一个神秘的水坑
in the highlands of central Italy.
他们声称这个小湖和周围的20个凹坑
They claim the small lake and some 20 nearby craters
是流星撞击的结果
are the results of meteorite fragments.
但这个证据远不足以让人信服
But the evidence is far from conclusive.
有人认为这些凹坑是古代人的贮水池
Some think the craters are ancient manmade reservoirs.
还有人怀疑它们只是二战时期的东西
Others suspect they only date back to World War II.
某些凹坑的迹象
- There's ordinance from some of the craters
说明了它们实际上是炸弹坑
that suggests that they are actually bomb craters.
问题是，这里曾经是
- The problem is, it's in a place
人口密集的地方
where there have been a lot of people.
它也许是一个贮水坑
And it was perhaps used as a watering hole.
它是人类活动
It's been so overprinted by human activity,
留下的遗迹
and I don't know if that one will ever be resolved.
它只是一个凹坑而已
But it certainly could be a crater.
斯兰特弹坑撞击假说里，有许多经不起推敲的地方
- One of the weakest parts of the Sirente crater impact hypothesis
其中之一是根本没有发现撞击矿物
is that the shocked minerals simply have not been found.
没有明显证据能说明曾发生过突然的撞击
There's no clear evidence that there was a whammo type impact there.
无论是不是宇宙撞击
narrator: Cosmic impact or not,
康斯坦丁见到奇观
Constantine's vision is considered
被公认是人类历史上最关键的事件之一
one of the most pivotal events in human history.
没有这个事件
- Had it not been for this event,
基督教能成为在欧洲占统治地位的宗教
would Christianity have become the dominant religion of Europe
然后扩展到美洲吗？
and then spread to the Americas?
这很难说
It's hard to say.
但显而易见的是，这次事件对促使康斯坦丁
But it's easy to say that this one event was pivotal
广泛支持基督教
in forcing Constantine
起到关键性的作用
to fully embrace the Christian religion.
=========翻译/时间轴:annwayili=========
（如有不当，请多包涵，不吝指导！谢谢！）
我们居住的星球
narrator: We live on a planet
是宇宙长期作用的产物
ceaselessly shaped by the cosmos
偶尔受到侵入者的攻击
and occasionally by invaders raining down fire.
太空力量对人类历史的改变
The power of space to alter human history
存在着争议
remains controversial.
也存在着这样的问题：它多久会发生？
But the question remains: how often does it happen?
对全新世撞击工作组的成员来说
For members of the Holocene Impact Working Group,
答案就是：比主流科学公认的
the answer is: far more frequently
更为频繁得多
than mainstream science currently accepts.
在最近的10,000至15,000年间
- So impacts over the course of human civilization
在对人类文明的影响方面
in the last 10,000 to 15,000 years,
我们毫不犹豫地相信
there's no question in our minds,
撞击在人类的进化
have played an important role
和人类文明的演变中
in the development of human evolution
扮演着一个重要的角色
and the evolution of human civilization.
但其它人对此强烈反对
narrator: But others hotly disagree.
外星物体没有足够的可能
- There just aren't enough potential impactors out there
曾撞击过地球
to have hit the Earth.
其发生的概率--
And the kind of rates that they're suggesting-
直径数公里的物体撞击地球
kilometer-sized objects hitting the Earth
每几千年就会发生--
every few thousand years-
即是说，如果万一有物体
I mean, if there were enough objects
要撞击地球
to hit the Earth at that rate,
我们只是擦肩而过
we'd be getting near-misses.
每年都有一两次
We'd be getting objects that size
我们以为物体
coming between the Earth and the Moon,
要在地球和月球之间穿过
you know, one or two of those a year.
但我们从未见过其发生
And we've never seen anything like that.
所以，这种概率不存在
The rate just isn't there.
激烈的争论会一直继续
narrator: The debate will continue to rage,
可能会持续到人类文明的末日来临之际
perhaps until the very end of human civilization.
届时，宇宙对人类历史改变的结束
But will that end be a gradual demise
会是逐渐消亡的形式
or a sudden violent demonstration
还是突然的轰轰烈烈的方式？
of how space can change history?